Sartre!
Sartre?
I'll say "Sartre".
My name is Joakim, welcome to this lesson on Jean-Paul Sartre-one of the greatest philosophers of the 20th century.
In October 1945, Jean-Paul Sartre (1905-1980) gave a lecture entitled "existentialism is a humanism".
The event was an enormous success and the influx of curious was huge.
The hard pressure to fit in the room caused the ticket door and large parts of the interior to be struck in pieces.
The lecturer himself succeeded in the right and constantly pushing himself between the audience
Before he could start his speech with an hour delay.
Existentialism was born.
Sartre received his education at a noble school in Paris and later came to work as a high school teacher in philosophy.
He was a little over 1.50 long, skewed heavily and described himself as ugly.
Almost always he went dressed in black polo, baskets, dark pants and jacket
- A clothing that became an existential fashion.
Everything we do and perceive is charged with emotions and personal meaning.
It is our consciousness that determines what is an event and what is background noise.
Suppose you will meet a friend in a cafe but that she never shows up.
Then her absence becomes an event, but only for you.
None of the other café guests will respond to your friend missing.
For you, the other visitors will only become insignificant background in this context.
It is actually remarkable that something that does not exist (in this example your missing friend)
May be of great importance to us.
Sartre, with his philosophy, tried to describe the basic features of human existence,
Why his philosophy is called "existentialism".
He built on, and deepened, the thoughts and concepts that Søren Kierkegaard
So we humans are not created for anything, we just exist.
First, we must live, exist, before we can get a definition, an essence.
This is central to existentialism, and was formulated by Sartre as "the existence precedes the essence".
For the thing it is the opposite.
"The problem is not what life has done to us but what we do of what life has done to us."
We humans are thus free, but freedom in the existential sense is no unlimited freedom.
We will never be able to do everything we want, we will never be able to fly or get super powers.
Then freedom could not be separated from dream or imagination.
Freedom instead arises in the meeting with the given conditions, what we cannot do anything about.
That we are born by our parents and with some genetic traits, that we are born in a particular country in a certain period of time
- These are the conditions of life.
These circumstances are also the starting point of freedom.
All this, Sartre said, is our fate.
And freedom arises precisely in the meeting with fate, with our assets and restrictions.
Of course, freedom is not just a state of mind, but it is in internal freedom begins.
- That the essence therefore precedes existence.
For Sartre, it is the opposite.
We are thrown out in a world where we exist and "... man is nothing but what she does".
What is primarily distinguished man from the thing is that we are aware
And can reflect on ourselves and our situation.
In contrast to the thing, we also have the ability to imagine the world differently,
Being able to see nothing - what is not but that could be.
According to Sartre, it is precisely the ability to imagine the world differently that enables freedom.
For our actions is affected by what is not yet;
If you decide to become a doctor, it does not mean that you are already a doctor.
What is not will be the driving force of the act itself, what we strive for.
They can only be "in themselves", which means that they are guided by their instincts and drives.
Existing means being able to relate to different modes of action and situations;
Being able to choose between one and the other action and see alternatives to the prevailing situation.
According to Sartre, we are in an absurd and meaningless world that we do not understand.
This is a world that lacks direction, goals and guidelines.
There is no God to rely on, but we are completely left out to ourselves.
The meaning and values we may still find are therefore only our own inventions.
Sartre does not mean that this makes life meaningless.
He believes that morality is important for our lives but that it is up to ourselves to invent it.
The same goes for the meaning of life - it does not exist in itself, but must be chosen by each individual.
It is thus not objective, but every person chooses his own meaning with their own life.
By showing the way we also show the option.
If the choice is right for me, it may also be right for you.
Here the collectivist Sartre is glimpsed.
He was also very politically engaged, far out on the left.
The fact that the world itself lacks values is the logical consequence of an atheistic philosophy.
It is man who gives things his meaning as we have now taken the role God previously had
in the human performance.
Things therefore, like the humans, are basically meaningless.
Despite this, we are constantly busy trying to control things.
We have plans for things.
Only therefore they mean something to us.
But there are situations where we clearly feel the excess of things.
How meaningless do not get small memory things, newspaper clippings
And anonymous photographs in a relative's estate?
The dearest memories end up in the heirs' black garbage bags.
The whole existence sometimes becomes like a death estate after God where all things become meaningless.
The world is no longer a creation but a pile of debris, says Sartre.